{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Theory_of_Computation — Slot 4 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Theory_of_Computation — Slot 4",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let &lt; M &gt; denote an encoding of an automaton M. Suppose that \\(\\Sigma =\\{0,1\\}\\). Which of the following languages is/are NOT recursive? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L= \\{ \\langle M \\rangle \\mid M \\text{ is a DFA such that } L(M)=\\emptyset \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L= \\{ \\langle M \\rangle \\mid M \\text{ is a DFA such that } L(M)=\\Sigma ^ * \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L= \\{ \\langle M \\rangle \\mid M \\text{ is a PDA such that } L(M)=\\emptyset \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L= \\{ \\langle M \\rangle \\mid M \\text{ is a PDA such that } L(M)=\\Sigma ^ * \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L= \\{ \\langle M \\rangle \\mid M \\text{ is a PDA such that } L(M)=\\Sigma ^ * \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357440/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-12#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that \\(L_1\\) is a regular language and \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language. Which one of the following languages is NOT necessarily context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cap L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cdot L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cup L_2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357451/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Minimum number of states required in DFA accepting binary strings not ending in \"101\" is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331452/isro2020-41\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The language which is generated by the grammar \\(S \\rightarrow a S a\\mid b S b\\mid a\\mid b\\) over the alphabet of {a,b} is the set of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Strings that begin and end with the same symbol</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>All odd and even length palindromes</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>All odd length palindromes</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All even length palindromes</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>All odd length palindromes</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331445/isro2020-39\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Every subset of a regular set is regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Every finite subset of non-regular set is regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The union of two non regular set is not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Infinite union of finite set is regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Every finite subset of non-regular set is regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331442/isro2020-38\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Context free languages are closed under <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>union, intersection</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>union, kleene closure</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>intersection, complement</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>complement, kleene closure</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>union, kleene closure</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331440/isro2020-37\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following language.<br><br>\nL={\\(x \\in \\{a,b\\}^*|\\) number of a's in x divisible by 2 but not divisible by 3}<br><br>\nThe minimum number of states in DFA that accepts L is _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333180/gate2020-cs-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages. <br>\\(L_1=\\{wxyx|w,x,y \\in (0+1)^+\\}\\) <br>\\(L_2=\\{xy|x,y \\in (a+b)^*,|x|=|y|,x\\neq y\\}\\) <br> <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but not regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but  \\(L_2\\) is not context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333199/gate2020-cs-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following languages are undecidable? Note that \\(\\left \\langle M \\right \\rangle\\) indicates encoding of the Turing machine \\(M\\). <br><br> \\(L_1=\\{\\left \\langle M \\right \\rangle|L(M)=\\varnothing \\}\\)<br> \\(L_2=\\){\\(\\left \\langle M,w,q \\right \\rangle|M\\) on input w reaches state q in exactly 100 steps} <br>\\(L_3=\\{\\left \\langle M \\right \\rangle|L(M) \\;is \\; not \\; recursive\\}\\) <br> \\(L_4=\\{\\left \\langle M \\right \\rangle|L(M) \\;contains \\; at \\; least\\; 21 \\; members\\}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1,L_3 \\; and \\; L_4 \\; only\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\; and \\; L_3 \\; only\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_2 \\; and \\; L_3 \\; only\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_2,L_3 \\; and \\; L_4 \\; only\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1,L_3 \\; and \\; L_4 \\; only\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333205/gate2020-cs-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the language \\(L=\\{a^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\cup \\{a^nb^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\) and the following statements. <br><br>\nI. L is deterministic context-free.<br>\nII. L is context-free but not deterministic context-free.<br>\nIII. L is not LL(k) for any k.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333221/gate2020-cs-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements.<br><br>\nI.  If \\(L_1\\cup L_2\\) is regular, then both \\(L_1 \\; and \\; L_2\\) must be regular.<br>\nII. The class of regular languages is closed under infinite union.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333223/gate2020-cs-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following regular expressions represents the set of all binary strings with an odd number of 1's? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(((0+1)^* 1(0+1)^*1)^*10^*\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((0^*10^*10^*)^*0^*1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(10^*(0^*10^*10^*)^*\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((0^*10^*10^*)^*10^*\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((0^*10^*10^*)^*10^*\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "As per Official GATE CSE 2020 Answer key _MTA (Marks to All)<br><a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333224/gate2020-cs-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(\\Sigma\\) be the set of all bijections from {1,...,5} to {1,...,5}, where \\(id\\) denotes the identity function, i.e. \\(id(j)=j,\\forall j\\). Let \\(\\circ\\) denote composition on functions. For a string \\(x = x_1x_2 ... x_n \\in \\Sigma ^n, n \\geq 0\\), let \\(\\pi(x) = x_1\\circ x_2\\circ ... \\circ x_n\\). Consider the language \\(L = \\{x \\in \\Sigma ^* | \\pi(x) = id\\}\\). The minimum number of states in any DFA accepting L is _________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "120",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302800/gate2019-cs-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sets:<br><br>\nS1: Set of all recursively enumerable languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.<br>\nS2: Set of all syntactically valid C programs.<br>\nS3: Set of all languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.<br>\nS4: Set of all non-regular languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.\n<br><br>\nWhich of the above sets are uncountable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>S1 and S2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>S3 and S4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>S2 and S3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>S1 and S4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>S3 and S4</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302814/gate2019-cs-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following languages over \\(\\Sigma =\\{a,b\\}\\) is NOT context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ww^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nb^nw^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^nb^i|i \\in \\{n,3n,5n\\},n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302817/gate2019-cs-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}